Guide to the Lisbet Tellefsen Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lisbet Tellefsen papers
1980-2008
1988-1994
GEN MSS 1431
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.67
(8 boxes)
The collection consists of material created and collected by Lisbet Tellefsen. Many of the materials center around the creation of Aché, which was first issued in 1989 as a journal and existed as a collective in the Bay Area until 1994. The rest of the materials generally relate to allied groups and other events that Tellefsen participated in and helped to organize, such as the National Black Gay and Lesbian Conference's Video Project.
Tellefsen, Lisbet, 1961-
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material created and collected by Lisbet Tellefsen. Many of the materials center around the creation of Aché, which was first issued in 1989 as a journal and existed as a collective in the Bay Area until 1994. The rest of the materials generally relate to allied groups and other events that Tellefsen participated in and helped to organize, such as the National Black Gay and Lesbian Conference's Video Project.
Lisbet Tellefsen
Lisbet Tellefsen, political activist, feminist, and community organizer, is a Bay Area native. Tellefsen co-founded the journal Aché, along with Pippa Fleming, and she has worked as an editor, recording engineer, and producer, receiving a number of awards for her service to the lesbian and gay community.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 8 (floppy disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Bolerium Books in 2012.
Arrangement
Arranged roughly in the order received.
Aché: a free publication for black lesbians.
The journal Aché was co-founded by Lisbet Tellefsen and Pippa Fleming in 1989. The organization was originally headquartered in Albany, California. The publication utilized a few varient subtitles throughout its lifetime (1989-1993), including "A journal for lesbians of African descent," and it was distributed to subscribers in eight different countries.
In addition to Tellefsen and Fleming, there were many other collaborators who helped to run Aché until the time that it was dissolved officially, in 1994, as a non-profit organization. In 1990, the Aché leadership was listed as:
DeeAnne Davis
Reatha Fowler
Winn Gilmore
Rebecca Hall
Amana Johnson
Teri Lethridge
Lisbet Tellefsen
Janet Wallace
Skye Ward
Jean Wesinger
Erica Wilson
See Aché material (box 3, folder 143) for a full narrative overview of the group.
Separated Materials
An additional two boxes of printed materials arrived with the collection and have been cataloged separately. Those materials can be found by searching ORBIS for the phrase: "From the Lisbet Tellefsen papers".
Aché; Lesbian activists -- United States; African American lesbians -- California -- San Francisco Bay Area; Periodicals -- Publishing -- United States; Born digital; Editors; LGBTQ resource; Tellefsen, Lisbet, 1961-; Fleming, Pippa; Lorde, Audre, 1934-1992; National Black Gay & Lesbian Conference
- May 2012 Acquisition
  - Aché correspondence received, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Artwork for Aché and event leaflets, circa 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Personal artwork and artwork for Aché, circa 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - Barbara Smith - Kitchen Table Press, circa 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - Essex Hemphill, circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - Audre Lorde, circa 1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Aché miscellaneous correspondence, 1990–1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - ULOAH: United Lesbians of African Heritage, circa 1991-1999 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - The first black lesbian conference, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - National Black Gay and Lesbian Conference, circa 1988-1997 (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
  - National Coalition of Black Gays, circa 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - National Association of Black and White Men Together, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Shango Project: National Archives for Black Lesbians and Gay Men, Bloomington, Indiana, 1994 June 27; 1 printed email (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Nia Collective: Lesbians of African descent, 1989–1991; 2002 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes photographs
  - Lesbian Herstory Archives, circa 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - GLHS: Gay Lesbian Historical Society of Northern California, 1991–1998 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Gay Out Productions, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - GMAD: Gay Men of African Descent, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Black Women's Health Project, 1988–1993 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bayblag: Bay Area Black Lesbians + Gays, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - AAGLCA: African-American Gay + Lesbian Cultural Alliance, circa 1991 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Black Gay Lesbian Leadership forum/conference, circa 1991-2008 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Kitchen Table Press, circa 1988 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - LGADDA: Lesbians Gays of African Descent for Democratic Action, circa 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - LAGADU/HABARI - Lesbians and Gays of African Descent United, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Latina Lesbian organizations, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Black Lesbian Gay Weekend (D.C.), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Film - miscellaneous files, circa 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Film - Michelle Parkerson, circa 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Film - Pratibha Parmar [A Place of Rage], 1991–1992 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Film - Sweet Sugar Rage, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Film - Tiny Ruby, international sweethearts of rhythm, circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Film - Marlon Riggs, circa 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Film - Alice Walker, circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Pomo Afro Homos, circa 1991-1997 (Box 1, Folder 41-43)
    Biographical / Historical
    Gay theatre troupe from San Francisco
  - Audre's Memorial, circa 1992 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Includes a flyer for a memorial held in honor of Audre Lorde on November 29, 1992, at Modern Times Bookstore in San Francisco.
  - 4 Big Girls, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Performance troupe from Seattle
    Includes a script for "Bigger than a Bread Box"
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - ASE Drumming Circle, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - Gwen Avery, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Aftists (performers) press/packets - BOA/Brat Pack, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - Casselberry Dupré, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Aftists (performers) press/packets - Rachel Bagby [removed from red folder], undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - India Cooke, circa 1991 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - Blackberri, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - Wayne Corbitt, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - Melanie DeMore, circa 1993 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - Laura Love, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - Deidre McCalla, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Artists (perfomers) press/packets - Rashida Oji, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - Randle, Vicki, circa 1993 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - Toshi Reagon, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - Redwood, circa 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - Root Wymn, circa 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - Anna Deavere Smith, 1993–1995 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Artists (performers) press/packets - Belinda Sullivan, circa 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Submissions - Erotica submissions, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Submissions - Book/film reviews/art critique, undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Submissions - Health, spirituality, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Submissions - Poetry submissions, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Submissions - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Submissios - Artist statements, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Submissions - Bulletin board, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Submissions - Other publications calls for submissions, undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Submissions - Contributions by Black Gay Men, circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Submissions - Terri L. Jewell, 1990–1995 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Film resources, circa 1993-1999 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Film resources - film/video, 1991–1994 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Film resources - Daughters of the Dust, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Film resources - Shari Frilot/mix, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Film resources - Miscellaneous press packet materials [empty] (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Film resources - Third World newsreel, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Film Resources - LOC/WOC film resources, 1991–1996 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Film resources - Margaret Daniel, circa 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Karen Williams, comedian, circa 1994 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    Clippings
  - "Thing" T-shirt and postcard, undated (Box 2, Folder 83)
    The text "THING / she knows who she is" is printed on the front of the T-shirt. The postcard is by THING publishing, titled "bubblehead por.trit" by Lee Kay, and it features a drawing of RuPaul on the front.
  - Photographic prints
    - Assorted photos, some with ID [identification], of Aché staff, undated (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Photos of board retreat, circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Aché staff at Lisbet's house, 1990; 1 photographic print (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Aché journal committee, undated (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Photos for Aché's 1st anniversary event poster, undated (Box 2, Folder 88)
      Four photographic prints of Rachel Bagby and Diane Ferlatte.
    - Audre Lorde Memorial - @ Modern Times Bookstore, S.F., 1992 November 29 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Essex Hemphill @ The Woman's Bldg, SF, 1992 June 13 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Women's Institute, 1992 February (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - A Drag King Thang @ La Pena, Berkeley, 1992 October 28 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Aché buttons, undated; 5 items (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Pippa Anne Fleming, undated (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Lisbet Tellefsen, undated (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Origins of Aché - early notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 96-97)
  - Subscription forms/mailing lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 98-100)
  - Aché financial records, including receipts and bills, circa 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 101-105)
  - Aché financial records, including receipts, circa 1989-1992 (Box 3, Folder 106-110)
  - Aché checkbooks, 1991–1992; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Checkbooks, receipts, notebook, etc., circa 1989-1993 (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - Event income, undated (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Merchandise/T-shirt sales, undated (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Aché subscriptions, undated (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Aché receipts, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Aché files, 1991–1992 (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Bookstore sales, undated (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - Aché office, undated (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - Ad package, undated (Box 3, Folder 120)
  - Mailing lists / subscribers, undated (Box 3, Folder 121)
  - Office phone logs, undated (Box 3, Folder 122)
  - Office insurance package, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 123)
  - Aché events / flyers [removed from binder], undated (Box 3, Folder 124)
  - Luna Institute: National Black Lesbian Conference, undated (Box 3, Folder 125)
  - Kenya Briggs, undated (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - Andrea Canaan, 1993 June 2 (Box 3, Folder 127)
  - Tobe Melora Correal, undated (Box 3, Folder 128)
  - Shari Harris, undated (Box 3, Folder 129)
  - Women of Color Organizations Projects: A National Directory, undated (Box 3, Folder 130)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, research info, undated (Box 3, Folder 131)
  - Aché rubber stamps, undated; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 132)
  - Earthlyn Manuel - Board of Directors, undated (Box 3, Folder 133)
  - Loose papers on incorporation, undated (Box 3, Folder 134)
  - Promo material, undated (Box 3, Folder 135)
  - Aché Press / Articles / Mentions, undated (Box 3, Folder 136)
  - Aché - IRS 501(c)3, undated (Box 3, Folder 137)
  - Aché tax materials for 1991, 1991–1992 (Box 3, Folder 138)
  - Aché material, 1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 139)
  - Aché press / articles, undated (Box 3, Folder 140)
  - Stationery, undated (Box 3, Folder 141)
  - Aché website notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 142)
  - Aché material, 1990; 1993 (Box 3, Folder 143)
    Contains two items: a narrative overview of Aché, prepared to seek funding from the Vanguard Foundation, which includes background history, goals and objectives, structure of the organization, as well as funding and financial information; and a "A Guide to Black Gay & Lesbian Video/Film" from the 1993 Sixth Annual National Black Gay & Lesbian Conference.
  - Skye Ward / outreach coordinator - Resources / organization development, undated (Box 3, Folder 144)
  - Skye Ward, undated (Box 3, Folder 145)
  - Dissolution papers, 1994 September (Box 3, Folder 146)
  - Federal tax exempt status, undated (Box 3, Folder 147)
  - Proposals - Office improvement project - Aché, undated (Box 3, Folder 148)
  - Proposals - Subscription improvement project, undated (Box 3, Folder 149)
  - Proposals - Individual donors project, undated (Box 3, Folder 150)
  - Proposals - Volunteers projects, undated (Box 3, Folder 151)
  - Grant info, undated (Box 3, Folder 152)
  - Grant info - Women's foundation, undated (Box 3, Folder 153)
  - Aché organization development, grants, board / meeting notes [removed from binder], undated (Box 3, Folder 154-155)
  - International outreach/networking - South Africa - Glow letter, undated (Box 4, Folder 156)
  - International outreach/networking - Lanvola - LOC [Lesbians of Color] group from New Zealand, undated (Box 4, Folder 157)
  - International outreach / networking - Afro-German materials, undated (Box 4, Folder 158)
    Photographs, postcards, and letters, including a typewritten letter to Tellefsen from Audre Lorde, written in Berlin and dated 5/13/90.
  - International outreach / networking, undated (Box 4, Folder 159)
  - UK / England, WOC [Women of Color] / LOC [Lesbians of Color], undated (Box 4, Folder 160)
  - UK / England, WOC / LOC - Black Lesbian Gay Centre (London), undated (Box 4, Folder 161)
  - UK / England, WOC / LOC - England Black ♀♀'s ♂, undated (Box 4, Folder 162)
  - UK / England, WOC / LOC - Black Women's Network (London), undated (Box 4, Folder 163)
  - Aché files, undated (Box 4, Folder 164)
  - Aché files from Jul/Aug. '90, vol. 2, no. 4, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 165)
  - Aché files from Oct/Nov. '91, vol. 3, no. 5, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 166)
  - Aché journal photos, undated (Box 4, Folder 167)
    Three photographs: two duplicate prints feature photographer Jean Weisinger and musician Joy Gamble; the other photograph is of Rev. Afua Chinue Ifama.
  - Aché editors / journal committee members - Skye Ward, undated (Box 4, Folder 168)
  - Aché editors / journal committee members - Winn Gilmore, undated (Box 4, Folder 169)
    Including a computer printout copy of "The Dinner Guest."
  - Aché editors / journal committee members - Debra K. Floyd, undated (Box 4, Folder 170)
  - Aché editors / journal committee members - DeeAnne Davis, editor, undated (Box 4, Folder 171)
    Including three photographs of Davis.
  - Aché editors / journal committee members - Blake C. Aarons, clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 172)
  - Aché Puzzle Page by Lisbet, undated; 1 page (Box 4, Folder 173)
    "See if you can find the last name of these 22 authors."
  - Aché editors / journal committee members - Storme Webber, undated (Box 4, Folder 174)
  - Aché journal / income notes - Octavia Butler, clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 175)
  - Aché journal committee / notes - Submissions / writings, undated (Box 4, Folder 176)
  - Aché journal committee / notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 177)
  - Aché journal committee / notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 178)
  - Aché journal submissions, undated (Box 5, Folder 179-181)
  - Pages from Aché vol. 1, number 1, 1989 February (Box 6, Folder 182)
  - Aché layouts
    - Volume 1, number 1, 1989 February (Box 6, Folder 183)
    - Volume 1, number 2, 1989 March (Box 6, Folder 184)
    - Volume 1, number 3, 1989 April (Box 6, Folder 185)
    - Volume 1, number 4, 1989 May (Box 6, Folder 186)
    - Volume 1, number 5, 1989 June (Box 6, Folder 187)
      Though this layout cover lists the date as "April 1989," these materials are actually the layouts for the June issue.
    - Volume 1, number 7, 1999 August (Box 6, Folder 188)
    - Volume 1, number 8, 1989 September (Box 6, Folder 189)
    - Volume 1, number 9, 1989 October (Box 6, Folder 190)
    - Volume 1, number 10, 1989 November (Box 6, Folder 191)
    - Volume 1, number 11, 1989 December (Box 6, Folder 192)
    - Volume 2, number 1, 1990 February (Box 6, Folder 193)
    - Volume 2, number 2, 1990 March–1990 April (Box 6, Folder 194)
    - Volume 2, number 3, 1990 May–1990 June (Box 7, Folder 195)
    - Volume 2, number 4, 1990 July–1990 August (Box 7, Folder 196)
    - Volume 2, number 5, 1990 September–1990 October (Box 7, Folder 197)
    - Volume 2, number 6, 1990 November–1990 December (Box 7, Folder 198)
    - Volume 3, number 1, 1991 February–1991 March (Box 7, Folder 199)
    - Volume 3, number 4, 1991 August–1991 September (Box 7, Folder 200)
    - Volume 4, number 1, 1992 February–1992 March (Box 7, Folder 201)
    - Volume 4, number 2, 1992 May–1992 June (Box 7, Folder 202)
  - Poster (for "Sisters of the Night," 1995 Halloween party) and cover art from Aché vol. 1, no. 1 cover (2 copies), 1989; 1995, undated (Box 7, Folder 203)
  - "Tribal Expressions" A Celebration of 2 Years of Aché, mock-ups, undated (Box 7, Folder 204)
  - "The Party" posters (3), 1990 June 30 (Box 7, Folder 205)
  - "An evening with filmmaker Aarin Busch" posters (3), undated (Box 7, Folder 206)
  - "Tribal Connexions" poster, 1991 March 2 (Box 7, Folder 207)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 7, Folder 208)
    Includes artwork for Aché layouts; photographs (two photographs of Rev. Afua Chinue Ifama, and one photograph of Imani Harrington); and additional manuscript pages.
  - Floppy disks, 1989–1994
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original computer disks are restricted and may only be seen with approval from the appropriate curator until the files have been imaged and reviewed. Contact Access Services for further information.
    - Aché stuff 7/94, 1994 July; 1 (Box 8, Folder 209)
    - Aché grants, poetry, articles, calendars, etc., undated; 1 (Box 8, Folder 209)
    - Aché $$ books 1989, '90, '91, '92, '93 (Quicken 3.0), 1989–1993; 1 (Box 8, Folder 209)